Guide to the Cornwall Miscellanea 1779-2003 MS 011 MS 011 MS 011
Cornwall Historical Society
- Photographic Materials
  - Photographs
    - Topics
      - Sedgwick-Related Photographs
        - Decoration Ceremony, 1900 (Box OS 2, Folder 10)
          Photograph of the dedication ceremony of the Sedgwick Monument.
        - Grave Decoration, May 30, 1900 (Box OS 2, Folder 11)
          Close-up photograph of Gen. John Sedgwick's decorated grave.
        - West Point, N.D. (Box OS 2, Folder 12)
          View of West Point.
        - Portrait, N.D. (Box OS 2, Folder 13)
          Portrait of Gen. John Sedgwick.
        - Sedgwick Monument, N.D. (Box OS 4, Object 3)
          Photograph of the Sedgwick Monument in Cornwall Hollow.
      - Hurricane of 1938
        - Cochrane Store Damage, September 22, 1938, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 7)
          Photographs of storm damage in the area around Cochrane's Store in West Cornwall.
        - Barber Shop Damage, 1938 (Box 32, Folder 8)
          Photographs of the storm damage around a barber shop in West Cornwall.
        - Covered Bridge, 1938 (Box 32, Folder 9)
          Photographs of the high water level of the Housatonic River below the West Cornwall Covered Bridge.
        - West Cornwall Main Street Damage, 1938 (Box 32, Folder 10)
          Photographs of storm damage along Main Street in West Cornwall.
        - Yard of Nellie Cole, 1938 (Box 32, Folder 11)
          Photograph of Nellie Cole's flooded yard. Photo taken by P. Rogers.
        - Damaged Market, 1938 (Box 32, Folder 12)
          Photograph of the back of a damaged market building.
      - Flood of 1955
        - Larry Gates Photographs: Part I, August 1955-October 1955 (Box 32, Folder 13)
          Photographs of the damage caused by the Flood of 1955 taken by Larry Gates. The photographs focus on damage in West Cornwall.
        - Larry Gates Photographs: Part II, August 1955-September 1955 (Box 32, Folder 14)
          Photographs of storm damage taken in West Cornwall by Larry Gates.
        - Route 7 Damage, September 1955 (Box 32, Folder 15)
          Photograph of a sink hole in Route 7.
        - West Cornwall Main Street Damage, August 1955-October 1955 (Box 32, Folder 16)
          Photographs of flood damage along Main Street in West Cornwall.
        - West Cornwall Cleanup, September 1955 (Box 32, Folder 17)
          Photographs of cleanup efforts in West Cornwall after the Flood of 1955.
        - Railroad Damage, September 1955 (Box 32, Folder 18)
          Photographs of damaged railroad tracks in West Cornwall.
        - West Cornwall Localized Flooding, August 1955-October 1955 (Box 32, Folder 19)
          Photographs of flooded areas of West Cornwall.
        - Miscellaneous Damage, September 1955 (Box 32, Folder 20)
          Photographs of miscellaneous storm damage in Cornwall and Sharon.
      - Cemeteries
        - St. Bridget Cemetery, circa 1890 (Box 32, Folder 21)
          Copy of a photograph taken of the St. Bridget Cemetery in Cornwall Bridge.
        - North Cornwall Cemetery: Lydia Brewster Grave, June 2004 (Box 32, Folder 22)
          Photograph of the grave of Lydia Brewster (1849-1911), wife of Rollin M. Hubbard.
        - Cornwall Hollow Cemetery, July 4, 1937 (Box 32, Folder 23)
          Photograph of the Cornwall Hollow Cemetery, with a particular emphasis on the grave of Gen. John Sedgwick.
        - Calhoun Cemetery: Swift Graves, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 24)
          Photographs of the graves of Heman Swift, Henry Swift,, Polly Sackett Swift, Charles Swift, and Philo Swift in the Calhoun Cemetery in Cornwall Bridge.
        - Pest House Cemetery, 1926 (Box 32, Folder 25)
          Photograph of the graves in the Pest House Cemetery located in North Cornwall behind the meeting house.
        - Calhoun Cemetery: Revolutionary War Soldier and Settler Graves (Box 32, Folder 26)
          Photographs of the graves of William Tanner, Daniel Everest, Perez Bonney, Jr., Benjamin Dibble, and Timothy Johnson in the Calhoun Cemetery in Cornwall Bridge.
        - Allen Cemetery, 1994, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 27)
          Photographs of the Allen Cemetery in North Cornwall, including the Pioneer Monument.
          - Allen Cemetery, N.D. (Box OS 3, Folder 13)
            Oversize photograph of the Allen Cemetery in North Cornwall.
        - Cornwall Cemetery, 1927-1960, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 28)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Cemetery. One image depicts school children from East Cornwall visiting the grave of Henry Obookiah and another shows Emily E. Marsh following a memorial service to Obookiah. There are also photos of the North-Pierce graves taken by R.S. Myers.
        - Grave of William Chidester, N.D. (Box 35, Folder 10)
          Photograph of the grave of William Chidester in Canfield, Ohio. Chidester removed to Ohio from Cornwall in 1802.
        - Cornwall Cemetery: Grave of Obookiah, 1971 (Box 35, Folder 26)
          Black and white photographs of the grave of Henry Obookiah.
      - Glass Plate Negative Photographs
        - Ice Jam, March 1904 (Box 32, Folder 29)
          Photographs of an ice jam in the Housatonic River.
        - West Cornwall: Main Street, circa 1900, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 30)
          Photographs from along Main Street in West Cornwall.
        - West Cornwall: Covered Bridge, circa 1900 (Box 32, Folder 31)
          Photograph of the West Cornwall Covered Bridge over the Housatonic River.
        - Pine Street, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 32)
          Photographs taken along Pine Street in Cornwall Plain.
        - Housatonic River, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 33)
          Photographs of the Housatonic River, including images of the dam built by the Mallinson Shear Shop.
        - District 15 School, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 34)
          Photographs of the District 15 School on Lower River Road in West Cornwall.
        - Mallinson Shear Shop Flume, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 35)
          Detail of the flume, or dam, built by the Mallinson Shear Shop in West Cornwall.
        - Cochrane Store, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 36)
          Photograph of the interior of the Cochrane Store in West Cornwall.
        - Calhoun Farm, circa 1900, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 37)
          Photographs of the Calhoun family farm in Cornwall Plain.
        - Reuman-Pratt Barn, 1901 (Box 32, Folder 38)
          Photograph of the framing of the Reuman-Pratt barn on Cream Hill.
        - Sturges House, circa 1890 (Box 32, Folder 39)
          Photograph of the Sturges family standing outside their home on River Road in West Cornwall.
        - North Cornwall Meeting House, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 40)
          Photograph of the North Cornwall Meeting House following a winter storm.
        - Ice Skating Party, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 41)
          Photograph of people ice skating on a pond.
        - Housatonic Valley Institute Football Team, 1894, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 42)
          Photographs of the H.V.I. football team, including a team portrait featuring Charles Sandmeyer, John Sedgwick, Charles Swanson, Ralph Beers, and Brewster Hubbard.
        - Jewell Street, N.D. (Box 32, Folder 43)
          Photograph of an unidentified home along Jewell Street.
        - Riley-Baldwin House, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 1)
          Photograph of the Riley-Baldwin House.
        - Cream Hill Lake, circa 1900, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 2)
          Photographs of Cream Hill Lake, including people swimming and boating.
        - C.E. Wilcox and Sons Store, November 11, 1889 (Box 33, Folder 3)
          Photograph of the Wilcox Store in Cornwall Plain taken by John E. Calhoun.
        - Old Parsonage, circa 1895 (Box 33, Folder 4)
          Photograph of the "Old Parsonage."
        - Pine Swamp Falls, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 5)
          Photograph of Pine Swamp Falls in West Cornwall.
        - E. Bierce Homestead, circa 1901 (Box 33, Folder 6)
          Photograph of the Bierce family posing in front of their home on Cream Hill. The house was later owned by the Gannett family.
        - Boulders, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 7)
          Photographs of various boulders in Cornwall, including the Tilting Rock along Route 143.
        - Cornwall Creamery, circa 1900, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 8)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Creamery along Route 125. The building later served as a carpentry shop for the Calhoun family.
        - Cornwall Plain: Miscellaneous Buildings, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 9)
          Photographs of unlabeled buildings in Cornwall Plain.
        - Woolsey House, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 10)
          Photograph of the Woolsey House.
        - Edwin Bierce Cattle, circa 1900 (Box 33, Folder 11)
          Photograph of cows belonging to Edwin Bierce.
        - District 4 Schoolchildren, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 12)
          Photograph of students at the District 4 School with their teacher.
        - Vaill Farm, circa 1900 (Box 33, Folder 13)
          Photograph of Philander Vaill and Charlotte B. Smith Vaill in front of their home on Bunker Hill.
        - Cole Homestead, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 14)
          Photograph of the family of Everett Cole and Alice E. Potter Cole in front of their home on Dibble Hill. The house burned down in 1920.
        - George Crosby Family, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 15)
          Photographs of George Crosby and his family in West Cornwall.
        - William Bierce House, circa 1901 (Box 33, Folder 16)
          Photograph of William Bierce and his family posing in front of the house he built on Cream Hill.
        - William Brush, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 17)
          Photograph of William Brush and various family members posing in front of a barn.
        - West Cornwall Baseball Team, July 4, 1903 (Box 33, Folder 18)
          Team picture of the West Cornwall baseball team.
        - Sedgwick Monument, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 19)
        - Peltier Sawmill, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 20)
          Photographs of the Peltier Sawmill, which was located on Baldwin Brook in the Ballyhack.
        - William Hall Sawmill, circa 1900 (Box 33, Folder 21)
          Photograph of the sawmill operated by William Hall, which was located along the Hollenbeck River near Route 43.
        - Boarders at Remstein Place, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 22)
          Photograph of boarders who stayed at Remstein's in West Cornwall.
        - Kling Family, circa 1905 (Box 33, Folder 23)
          Photograph of the family of John Kling.
        - Cartwright Family, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 24)
          Photograph of Edward and William Cartwright.
        - Leavit Clark Homestead, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 25)
          Photograph of Leavit Clark and his wife posing in front of their home on Mohawk Mountain.
        - Saleski-Crosby Family, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 26)
          Photograph of members of the Saleski-Crosby family of West Cornwall playing chess.
        - William D. Bosler, Esq., N.D. (Box 33, Folder 27)
          Photograph of William D. Bosler posing in front of his law office.
        - Hattie Meriman, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 28)
          Photograph of Hattie Meriman and her family.
        - Miller Family, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 29)
          Photographs of the Miller family, including Freddy and Francis Miller as infants.
        - Clark Family Photographs, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 30)
          Personal photographs belonging to the Clark family of East Cornwall. Photos show the Clark farm and a parade.
        - Unspecified People, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 31)
          Unlabeled pictures of various people.
        - Unspecified Buildings, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 32)
          Unlabeled Cornwall buildings.
        - Landscapes, 1903, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 33)
          Photographs of various Cornwall landscapes, including Miner's Pond.
        - Tree on the Rock, N.D. (Box 33, Folder 41)
          Photograph of the "Tree on the Rock" in the Cathedral Pines.
      - Charcoal Industry
        - Colliers, N.D. (Box 34, Folder 20)
          Photographs of charcoal workers. Photos include colliers working and posing with their families.
        - Landscapes (Box 34, Folder 21)
          Photographs of Cream Hill showing the deforestation that resulted from charcoal making.
        - Charcoal Making, N.D. (Box 34, Folder 22)
          Photographs of the stacked firewood and earthen mounds needed for charcoal production.
      - Carol H. Goodfriend Album
        - Baird's Store, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 23)
          Photograph of Baird's Store in Cornwall Bridge.
        - St. Bridget's Church, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 24)
          Photograph of St. Bridget's Church in Cornwall Bridge.
        - St. Peter's Lutheran Church, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 25)
          Photograph of St. Peter's Lutheran Church in Cornwall Plain.
        - Trinity Conference Center, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 26)
          Photograph of the Trinity Conference Center on Lower River Road taken from Route 7.
        - West Cornwall Post Office, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 27)
          Photograph of the West Cornwall Post Office on Main Street.
        - National Iron Bank, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 28)
          Photograph of the National Iron Bank in Cornwall Bridge.
        - Cornwall Bridge Businesses, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 29)
          Photographs of Northwest Lumber, the Hitching Post, Cornwall Bridge Video, and the Housatonic Valley Rug Shop.
        - Cornwall Bridge Train Station, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 30)
          Photographs of the train station in Cornwall Bridge.
        - Town Green, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 31)
          Photographs of the Cornwall Town Green.
        - West Cornwall Covered Bridge, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 32)
          Photographs of the covered bridge over the Housatonic River.
        - West Cornwall Railroad Plaza, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 33)
          Photographs of the railroad plaza along Main Street in West Cornwall.
        - Yelping Hill, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 34)
          Photographs of the entrance to Yelping Hill and of the monument to the founders.
        - Housatonic River, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 35)
          Photographs of the Housatonic River.
        - Cream Hill Lake, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 36)
          Photograph of Cream Hill Lake taken during winter.
        - Cream Hill Farm, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 37)
          Photographs of Cream Hill Farm.
        - First Church, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 38)
          Photographs of the congregational church in Cornwall Plain.
        - Rumsey Hall, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 39)
          Photograph of the main building associated with Rumsey Hall along Pine Street.
        - Town Offices, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 40)
          Photograph of the town offices on Pine Street.
        - North Cornwall Meeting House, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 41)
          Photograph of the North Cornwall Meeting House.
        - Prentice Barns, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 42)
          Photographs of barns on Lake Road owned by the Prentice family.
        - West Cornwall Businesses, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 43)
          Photographs of Cold Spring Communications, Cornwall Bridge Pottery, West Cornwall Video, Barbara Farnsworth's Bookstore, Ian Ingersoll's Cabinet Shop, Cadwell's Corner Restaurant, and Yutzler's Country Store.
        - Mohawk Ski Area, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 44)
          Photograph of Mohawk Ski Area in East Cornwall.
        - Black Angus Farm, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 45)
          Photograph of Black Angus Farm on Cream Hill Road.
        - Scoville Farm, January 1995 (Box 34, Folder 46)
          Photograph of the Scoville family farm on Town Street in North Cornwall.
      - Organizations
        - First Aid Team, 1942 (Box 36, Folder 1)
          Photograph of Cornwall First Aid Team members Lou Frost, Marion C. Smith, Bertie Cartwright, and Dorothy Cook treating Eleanor S. Sureda.
        - Telephone Operators, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 2)
          Group photograph of Cornwall telephone operators Lil Swanson, Iva Jackson, Dorothy Sandmeyer, Cora Sandmeyer, Ethel Kimberly, and Florence Benedict.
        - Volunteer Fire Department, 1962 (Box 36, Folder 3)
          Photograph showing the dedication of the charter members plaque at the Cornwall Bridge Fire House. Members of the ceremony include Bertie Cartwright, Hazel Richter, Mary R. Smith, Robert Graham, Fred Bate Senior, William Behn, Frank Calhoun, Dick Dakin, and Chris Smith.
      - Transportation
        - Automobiles, 1911, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 4)
          Photographs of Cornwall residents and their automobiles. Photos include images of the Harrison family and their Model T, the Ives family "Speedster," Chub Nourse in his "Lightening Benz," and a 1900 Oldsmobile.
        - Carraiges, 1910, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 5)
          Photographs of Cornwall residents and their carraiges. Photos include an oil delivery wagon and peddler H. L. Gaylord.
        - Construction of Route 128, 1934 (Box 36, Folder 6)
          Photographs documenting the construction of Route 128 through Cornwall. Photos were taken by Mrs. William R. Brush.
      - 1989 Tornado
        - Downed Trees, July 1989 (Box 36, Folder 33)
          Photographs of downed trees around Cornwall, including the damage to the Cathedral Pines.
        - Pine Street Damage, July 1989 (Box 36, Folder 34)
          Photographs of storm damage along Pine Street.
        - Post Office, 1989 (Box 36, Folder 35)
          Photographs of storm damage near the post office on Bolton Hill Road.
        - Structural Damage, July 1989 (Box 36, Folder 36)
          Photographs of structural damage around Cornwall from the tornado.
    - Albums
      - Yutzler Family Album, ca. 1890 (Box OS 5)
      - Unidentified Family Albums, 1912-1916, ca. 1900 (Box OS 6)
        3 unidentified family albums and a blank album.
      - Rogers Family Album, 1918 (Box OS 6)
        Photographs of the Rogers family from North Cornwall.
      - Miner and Jessie Rogers Album, ca. 1900 (Box OS 6)
        Photograph album belonging to Miner and Jessie Rogers.
      - Lois M. Burton Album, 1912-1913 (Box OS 6)
        Photographs taken by Lois M. Burton.
      - Northwestern Connecticut Automobile Trip, ca. 1920 (Box OS 6)
        Photographs taken from a road trip around Northwestern Connecticut.
      - Cream Hill Photo Album, ca. 1920 (Box OS 6)
        Photographs taken around the Cream Hill area of Cornwall.
      - Baldwin Family Album, ca. 1890 (Box OS 7)
        Baldwin family photo album.
      - Marsh Family Album, ca. 1870 (Box OS 7)
        Collection of family photographs compiled by Emily E. Marsh.
      - Hart Family Album, ca. 1870 (Box OS 8)
        Hart family photo album.
  - Negatives
    - Memorial Day, 1992 (Box 36, Folder 17)
      Images of Memorial Day observations taken by Larry Gates.
    - Revere Teapot, September 1975 (Box 36, Folder 18)
      Images of a silver teapot in the collections of the Cornwall Historical Society attributed to Paul Revere.
    - Cutting Ice on the Housatonic River, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 19)
      Images of ice being cut from the frozen Housatonic River.
    - West Cornwall Covered Bridge, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 20)
      Images of repair work being done to the West Cornwall Covered Bridge.
    - Sedgwick Monument and Railroad Plaza (Box 36, Folder 21)
      Images of the Sedgwick Monument in Cornwall Hollow and the Railroad Plaza in West Cornwall.
    - Allen Cemetery, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 22)
      Images of the Allen Cemetery in North Cornwall.
    - Library Association Map Exhibit, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 23)
      Images of the map exhibition put on by the Library Association.
    - Covered Bridge Building and Hardware (Box 36, Folder 24)
      Image of Covered Bridge Building and Hardware in West Cornwall.
    - Flood of 1955 (Box 36, Folder 25)
      Images of storm damage following the Flood of 1955.
    - Cornwall Consolidated School Map Exhibit, August 1985 (Box 36, Folder 26)
      Images of the map exhibit held by the Cornwall Consolidated School.
    - Children's Cottage, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 27)
      Images of the building known as the "Children's Cottage."
    - Covered Bridge Building and Hardware (Box 36, Folder 28)
      Images of Covered Bridge Building and Hardware in West Cornwall.
    - Farm Scenes, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 29)
      Images of various farm scenes in Cornwall.
    - Foster House, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 30)
      Images of the Foster House in West Cornwall during its time functioning as an inn.
    - Cornwall Conservation Post, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 31)
      Image of the Cornwall Conservation Post.
    - Cunningham Tower, Mohawk State Park, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 32)
      Image of the Cunningham Tower in Mohawk State Park.
    - Ben Taylor House, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 37)
      Image of the Ben Taylor House taken by Armin Landeck.
    - Housatonic River, N.D. (Box 36, Folder 38)
      Images of the Housatonic River.
    - North Cornwall Meeting House, 1905 (Box 36, Folder 39)
      Image of the North Cornwall Meeting House and its congregation taken by James Henry Moser.
    - Cornwall Plain, circa 1880-2000, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 1)
      Photo negatives from Cornwall Plain. There are images of the Rumsey Hall School, the Congregational Church, the Lutheran Church, the Agricultural Fair, and various homes along Pine Street.
    - West Cornwall, circa 1900-1938, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 2)
      Photo negatives from images taken in West Cornwall. The collection includes scenes of the Yutzler family store, the Railroad Plaza, the covered bridge, the weir and factory owned by the J. Mallinson Shear Co., and various homes in the area.
    - Cornwall Hollow, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 3)
      Photo negatives from Cornwall Hollow. Images include the Yale-Dean wedding at the Cornwall Hollow Baptist Church, Margaret Hurlburt at the family garage, the Palmer Mill, the District 6 School, and various homes in the area.
    - Gen. John Sedgwick, circa 1864-1976, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 4)
      Photo negatives related to Gen. John Sedgwick. There are images of Sedgwick, Fort Sedgwick at Petersburg, James Hurlburt with Sedgwick's sword, and memorials in Sedgwick's honor in Cornwall Hollow and at Spotsylvania.
    - East Cornwall, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 5)
      Photo negatives from East Cornwall. Images include the Gaisman House, the Payne/Marsh House, the East Cornwall Baptist Church, and the Cunningham Tower on Mohawk Mountain.
    - Cream Hill, circa 1912- circa 1951, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 6)
      Photo negatives from Cream Hill. Images include the Hubbard, Scoville, and Pratt farms, as well as colliers and scenes from Cream Hill Lake.
    - North Cornwall, circa 1935, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 7)
      Photo negatives from North Cornwall. Images include scenes from the Ives and Scoville farms, as well as the Dutton House and Oliver Burnham House.
    - Cornwall Bridge, circa 1935, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 8)
      Photo negatives from Cornwall Bridge. Images include the old covered bridge, the train station, the Breen Store, and various homes in the area.
    - Cornwall Center, 1931, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 9)
      Photo negatives of the Ford House, the Harrison House, also known as "Plainview," the Kling House, the District 3 School, and the old Methodist Church.
    - Schools, 1940, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 10)
      Photo negatives of Cornwall district schools and school children.
    - People, 1887-1972, N.D. (Box 38, Folder 11)
      Photo negatives of miscellaneous Cornwall residents.
    - Exhibits, 1976-1991 (Box 38, Folder 12)
      Photo negatives of the Gold family quilt exhibit, the hooked rug exhibit, and the "Dutch" Yutzler exhibit at the Cornwall Historical Society.
    - North Cornwall Meeting House Centenary, August 1926 (Box 38, Folder 13)
      Photo negatives from the 100th anniversary of the North Cornwall Meeting House.